Guide to the North African Jewish Manuscript Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Fe?s, 1755-circa 1960; Series I
  - Fe?s (general)
    - Halakhic decision with regard to a partnership, Circa 1850-circa 1900; MS.1825.0200; 4 pages (2 blank); 20 centimeters. (Box 3, Folder 16)
      Place: Fès?. Incomplete document, appears to be part of a larger document. The discussion in the document doesn't include specifics and doesn't mention any names.
    - Document regarding collateral of land for a loan, Circa 1800-circa 1850; MS.1825.0203; 8 pages (5 blank); 23 centimeters. Pages are tied together with string. (Box 3, Folder 17)
      Place: Fès?. The manuscript is probably part of a book that deals with issues related to land. Based on the topic and the books being quoted, the manuscript was probably written by a great sage.
    - Halakhic discussion concerning inheritance rights, Circa 1850-circa 1900; MS.1825.0205; 4 columns (2 blank); 23 centimeters. (Box 3, Folder 18)
      Place: Fès. General discussion about inheritance rights of sons after the death of their father and of a woman after the death of her husband.
    - Various responsa with regard to property, Circa 1850-circa 1900; MS.1825.0206; 8 pages; 22 centimeters. Pamphlet. (Box 3, Folder 19)
      Place: Fès. The responsa are copied from a collection of novellae written at the beginning of the seventeenth century. This copy was written in Fès.
    - Various responsa, Circa 1850-circa 1900; MS.1825.0207; 4 pages; 23 centimeters. Crumbling edges with some loss of text. (Box 3, Folder 20)
      Place: Fès. Responsa from the same collection as MS.1825.0206
    - Five folios from a book on laws of slaughter, 1800s; MS.1825.0208; 12 pages; 16 centimeters. Pamphlet. Very fragile. One page is mostly missing except for a small fragment. (Box 3, Folder 21)
      Place: Fès or Meknès. The text includes the laws with commentary. It may be a copy of a work from the eighteenth century.
    - Copies of legal decisions concerning gifts, 1853; MS.1825.0210; 4 pages; 20 centimeters. (Box 3, Folder 22)
      Place: Sefrou, Fès. One decision (page 1) is dated 22 Iyar 1853 and signed on by Amram Elbaz and Amor Abiṭbol of Sefrou. A second decision is dated 8 Iyar 1853 and signed by Mosheh Attia and Shelomoh ha-Kohen of Fès.
    - Document concerning the sale of the right to build above a covered storehouse, Circa 1840-circa 1860; MS.1825.0212; 4 pages (2 blank); 20 centimeters. (Box 3, Folder 22)
      Place: Fès. The document deals with some of the issues involved in building on a roof of a house. One question is who is responsible for payment for a railing. Another issue relates to the need for windows to be facing the street and the Medina quarter if a second floor is to be added to a house. Some of the terms used in this document are distinctive of Fès. The witnesses in the sale were Mosheh Bibas and Sliman Yitshak ben Sabbah.
    - Document concerning a dispute over financing a business, Circa 1840-circa 1860; MS.1825.0213; 2 pages; 22 centimeters. Portion of the document is missing with some loss of text. (Box 3, Folder 22)
      Place: Fès. The dispute concerns a man who gave money to another person for a business. The man, to whom the money was given, ended up losing all of the money resulting in loss of the investment.
    - Copies of halakhic decisions with regard to different issues, Circa 1840-circa 1860; MS.1825.0218.1-.3; 10 pages (3 blank); 22 centimeters. (Box 3, Folder 23)
      Place: Fès. Among some of the issues are questions related to the community of Meknès, questions regarding partnership, decisions concerning a synagogue where children study, and questions regarding contributions to a privately owned synagogue.
    - Page from a chronicle of the Jews of Fès, 1700s; MS.1825.0219; 4 pages; 22 centimeters. Stains. Tears with loss of text. (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Document assigning a messenger to deliver a bill of divorce, 1888; MS.1825.0226; 2 pages; 23 centimeters. (Box 3, Folder 24)
      Place: Fès. The document is signed by Mordekhai Azulai and Mosheh Abisror.
    - Document affirming a gift, 1934; MS.1825.0241; 1 leaf; 23 centimeters. (Box 3, Folder 24)
      Place: Fès. The document includes a list of clothes given as a gift to a poor man by David Lahalluf. The document is signed by Shelomoh Sasson.
    - Liturgical poem, Circa 1880-circa 1900; MS.1825.0267; 4 pages; 15 centimeters. (Box 3, Folder 25)
      Place: Fès. The poem is signed by Yehonatan Hayim Tsiyon Mansano.
    - Legal document concerning the mortgage of property, 1898; MS.1825.0274; 2 pages; 37 centimeters. (Box 3, Folder 25)
      Place: Fès. The transactions involve various family members.
    - Legal document, 1922; MS.1825.0275; 4 pages (3 blank); 30 centimeters. (Box 3, Folder 25)
      Place: Fès. The document contains the testimony of Tamar bat Simhon regarding a dispute between her husband and her brother. The document is signed by Abba Attia and Shelomoh ben Shelomoh Eliyahu.
    - Legal document, 1894; MS.1825.0276; 4 pages (2 blank); 36 centimeters. (Box 32, Folder 1)
    - Documents regarding financial matters, 1879-1881; MS.1825.0281; 2 pages; 34 centimeters. (Box 3, Folder 26)
      Place: Fès. The first page has four documents regarding financial matters. The first one is from 1879 and it is likely that the other three are from the same year. They are all signed by Reuven Asulin. The second page has two documents. The first is from 1880 and is signed by Maimon Yisrael. The second one is from 1881, signed by Makhluf al-Kriyf.
    - Introduction to a book copied by Shalom Azulai concerning a collection of a famous and important anonymous rabbi, Circa 1850-circa 1900; MS.1825.0329; 2 pages; 21 centimeters. (Box 3, Folder 26)
      Place: Fès. Signed by Shalom Azulai.
    - Small collection of liturgical poems (piyyutim) with lists of names of women and men, Circa 1920-circa 1940; MS.1825.0336; 18 pages (6 blank); 17 centimeters. (Box 3, Folder 27)
      Place: Fès. The poems may have been written at the end of the nineteenth century. Two of the liturgical poems (piyyutim) were written by Yitshak ibn Danan, one was written by Refael Edre'i, and another, by a man named Masud, is a poem in honor of Rabbi Shimon Bar Yohai (Rashbi). At the end of the pamphlet there are two lists of names, one of women and one of men. It appears that these were members on the current rotation of the burial society, Hevrah Kadisha Rashbi. The list of women shows the custom in Fès of writing the family names of women using a feminine form: Kohena, Ismaila, etc.
    - Page from a collection of legal decisions of the Jewish Quarter of Fès, 1800s; MS.1825.0401; 2 pages; 30 centimeters. Worm-eaten and torn with some loss of text. (Box 3, Folder 28)
      Place: Fès. This document is a copy of an earlier document dating back to late sixteenth century or early senenteenth century. This document states that a man may marry a second wife if they are childless after ten years. Another decision on the same page states that a scribe of the court may not write a legal decision or a marriage contract without the presence of someone learned in Jewish law. Many sages that were expelled from Spain are mentioned.
    - Another page from a collection of laws of the Sephardic community of Fès relating to marriage contracts, 1800s; MS.1825.0402; 1 leaf; 29 centimeters. Worm-holes and tears with some loss of text. (Box 3, Folder 28)
      Place: Fès. This document is a copy of an earlier document dating back to late sixteenth century or early senenteenth century. Many early Sephardic rabbis of Morocco are mentioned.
    - Another page from a collection of Jewish laws of the city of Fès relating to the prohibition against Jews turning to non-Jewish legal authorities, 1800s; MS.1825.0403; 1 leaf; 29 centimeters. Worm-holes and tears with some loss of text. (Box 3, Folder 28)
      Place: Fès. This document is a copy of an earlier document dating back to late sixteenth century or early senenteenth century. This document also deals with the laws of levirate marriage. Many Moroccan rabbis are mentioned.
    - Legal decision, 1857; MS.1825.0405; 2 pages; 29 centimeters. Page is torn around the edges. (Box 3, Folder 28)
      Place: Fès. Signed by Masud [?] and Mosheh Mordekhai Maman.
    - Legal document concerning laws of money, 1763; MS.1825.0493; 4 pages (3 blank); 19 centimeters. (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Composition on the laws of "Orah Hayim" and customs from the city of Fès, including a celebration upon building a parapet, Circa 1880-circa 1900; MS.1825.0499; 12 pages; 16 centimeters. Some pages damaged with loss of text. (Box 3, Folder 30)
      Place: Fès. On pages 2 the document describes the custom of making a festive meal following building and making a blessing over a protective railing around a roof. The document includes many acronymns and abbreviations.
    - Draft of a document regarding the inheritance of a man who was killed on the way to Fès, Circa 1850-circa 1900; MS.1825.0501; 2 pages; 16 centimeters. Worm-eaten with some loss of text. (Box 3, Folder 31)
      Place: Fès. The man who wrote this document appears to have been nominated to sell the property of someone who was murdered. However, the governor of Sefrou would not grant Esther, the dead man's widow, the right to receive the income from the sale before she paid her late husband's debts. He also refused to return the money that was stolen when he was murdered. Esther then went to the Sultan of Morocco to seek his help. He responded to her request by sending one of his officials to go with her before the governor of Sefrou, presumably to ask him to cancel the dead man's debts. It appears that the governor did not yield and insisted that the debt be paid. On the verso is a liturgical poem about death.
    - Document regarding a dispute between the sages of Marrakech and the sages of Tétouan, Circa 1790-circa 1810; MS.1825.0510; 1 leaf; 21 centimeters. Edges torn and worm eaten with some loss of text. (Box 3, Folder 31)
      Place: Fès. The resolution is signed by sages of Fès or Meknès. The document shows how other communities regarded the rabbis of Fès and Meknès as authorities.
    - Fourteen legal documents, 1882; MS.1825.0511; 26 pages (5 blank); 18 centimeters. (Box 3, Folder 32)
      Place: Fès. They contain the signatures of various individuals.
    - Letter with regard to property in the city of Fès, 1860; MS.1825.0514; 4 pages (1 blank); 21 centimeters. (Box 3, Folder 33)
      Place: Fès. The letter is signed by Mosheh Attia and Shelomoh Attia.
    - Document apparently from Fès, 1889; MS.1825.0515; 4 pages (1 blank); 14 centimeters. (Box 3, Folder 33)
      Place: Fès?.
    - Document signed by Yehudah Mosheh Aflalo and Shelomoh Sasson, 1893; MS.1825.0517; 4 pages (3 blank); 16 centimeters. (Box 3, Folder 33)
      Place: Fès. Yehudah Mosheh Aflalo and Shelomoh Sasson were both scribes and witnesses.
    - Document signed by Abba Attia and Makhluf Turgeman, 1917; MS.1825.0526; 2 pages; 25 centimeters. (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Legal decision, 1918; MS.1825.0528; 4 pages (3 blank); 17 centimeters. (Box 3, Folder 34)
      Place: Fès. Signed by Abba Attia and [Shelomoh Haguel?].
    - Legal decision, 1853; MS.1825.0538; 4 pages (2 blank); 18 centimeters. (Box 3, Folder 34)
      Place: Fès. Signed by Mosheh Attia and Yitshak Azulai.
    - Document with regard to the needy of the town, 1872; MS.1825.0547; 2 pages; 18 centimeters. (Box 3, Folder 35)
      Place: Fès. Signed by Eliyahu Attia and one other.
    - Document signed by Yitshak ben Attia and another, 1886; MS.1825.0548; 2 pages; 18 centimeters. (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Document of sale of real estate, 1865; MS.1825.0549; 4 pages (2 blank); 32 centimeters. (Box 32, Folder 1)
      Place: Fès. The document is signed by Mosheh Attia and [?] ben Shoshan.
    - Document concerning the inheritance left by [Yisrael Amulam?] to his seven daughters, 1867; MS.1825.0550; 4 pages (2 blank); 30 centimeters. (Box 32, Folder 1)
      Place: Fès. One of the factors was that the mother of one of the daughters had died previously. The document is signed by Walid ben Sultan and others.
    - Document between Shelomoh Sultan and the Maimon family, 1918; MS.1825.0577; 4 pages (2 blank); 18 centimeters. (Box 3, Folder 35)
      Place: Fès. Signed by Yosef Kohen Skali.
    - Document concerning a room in the Jewish quarter (mellah), 1900; MS.1825.0589; 4 pages (2 blank); 15 centimeters. (Box 3, Folder 35)
      Place: Fès. Tsiyon ben Avraham Malul and Eliyahu ha-Kohen are mentioned. The document is signed by Abba Attia and Yedidyah Eziyni.
    - Group of eight documents concerning real estate, 1899-1915; MS.1825.0594; 4 pages (1 blank); 36 centimeters. (Box 32, Folder 2)
    - Letter from Tangier to Avraham Ben Shoshan in Fès, 1919; MS.1825.0597; 4 pages; 28 centimeters. (Box 32, Folder 2)
    - Document concerning a sale, 1875; MS.1825.0598; 4 pages (1 blank); 36 centimeters. (Box 32, Folder 3)
      Place: Fès. There are two additions on the bottom, The document is signed by Mosheh Attia and Yehudah Asulin, probably as witnesses.
    - Document with regard to the elimination of a debt, 1892; MS.1825.0650; 1 leaf; 20 centimeters. (Box 3, Folder 36)
      Place: Fès. Signed by rabbis of Fès.
    - Legal document cancelling an original marriage contract and replacing it with a new one, 1891; MS.1825.0651; 2 pages; 28 centimeters. Some damage to text. (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Itemized list of the inheritance left by Hayim Aflalo for his orphaned sons, Circa 1880-circa 1900; MS.1825.0652; 1 leaf; 23 x 27 centimeters. (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Copies of legal documents, 1897-1914; MS.1825.0654; 2 pages; 37 centimeters. (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Legal document concerning a woman's marriage contract, Circa 1900-circa 1920; MS.1825.0655; 4 pages (3 blank); 17 centimeters. (Box 3, Folder 37)
      Place: Fès. The original document is dated 1843 and is signed by Rahamim Hayim David ben Zimra. This copy has a short addition signed by Abba Attia.
    - Legal document, 1922; MS.1825.0656; 2 pages; 29 centimeters. (Box 3, Folder 37)
      Place: Fès. Contains the stamp of the rabbinic court of Fès, as well as a stamp of M. Hayon, probably the translator. Writing on the back in blue may be Spanish.
    - Copy of a legal document, 1922; MS.1825.0657; 4 pages (3 blank); 29 centimeters. (Box 3, Folder 37)
      Place: Fès. Contains the stamp of the rabbinic court of Fès and several signatures.
    - Legal document regarding collateral for a loan, 1907; MS.1825.0659; 1 leaf; 23 centimeters. (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Legal document from the Jewish quarter (mellah) of Fès, 1926; MS.1825.0663; 1 leaf; 32 centimeters. (Box 3, Folder 38)
      Place: Fès. Contains the stamp of the rabbinic court of Fès.
    - Halakhic novellae, Circa 1840-circa 1860; MS.1825.0674; 2 pages; 36 centimeters. Tears with loss of text. (Box 3, Folder 38)
      Place: Fès or Meknès. The document appears to be a page from a larger book written by a sage. It includes some mystical interpretations.
    - Legal document, Circa 1880-circa 1900; MS.1825.0676; 4 pages (3 blank); 12 centimeters. (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Legal document, Circa 1880-circa 1900; MS.1825.0678; 4 pages (3 blank); 16 centimeters. (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Legal document, Circa 1880-circa 1900; MS.1825.0680; 4 pages (3 blank); 12 centimeters. (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Legal document, Circa 1880-circa 1900; MS.1825.0681; 4 pages (3 blank); 20 centimeters. (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Legal document, Circa 1880-circa 1900; MS.1825.0682; 4 pages (3 blank); 30 centimeters. (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Legal document, Circa 1880-circa 1900; MS.1825.0683; 1 leaf; 30 centimeters. (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Legal document, Circa 1880-circa 1900; MS.1825.0684; 4 pages (3 blank); 24 centimeters. (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Legal document, Circa 1880-circa 1900; MS.1825.0685; 4 pages (3 blank); 24 centimeters. (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Legal document, Circa 1880-circa 1900; MS.1825.0687; 2 pages; 12 centimeters. (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Legal document, 1800s; MS.1825.0688; 4 pages (3 blank); 18 centimeters. (Box 3, Folder 41)
      Place: Fès. The document was signed in Fès. One of the people mentioned is from Tafilalt.
    - Document affirming a gift, 1895; MS.1825.0694; 1 leaf; 29 centimeters. Some stains. (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Two poetic lamentations (kinot) by Hayim ha-Kohen, Circa 1900-circa 1920; MS.1825.0772; 2 pages; 22 centimeters. (Box 3, Folder 42)
      Place: Fès?. Hayim ha-Kohen, possibly of Fès.
    - Letter with regard to a young woman who wishes to marry but has no dowry, 1927; MS.1825.0776; 1 leaf; 27 centimeters. (Box 3, Folder 42)
      Place: Fès. Written on the official stationery of the rabbinic court of Fès. The letter is signed by Rabbi Malka to Refael Attia in Rabat.
    - Legal document with regard to a piece of property in a business arrangement, 1913; MS.1825.0782; 4 pages (2 blank); 16 centimeters. (Box 3, Folder 43)
      Place: Fès. The business arrangement was between Reuven Attia and Hayim ben Makhluf [Sha'ayah?]
    - Legal document, 1915; MS.1825.0786; 1 leaf; 12 centimeters. (Box 3, Folder 43)
      Place: Fès?. Signed by Shelomoh ha-Kohen.
    - Legal document with regard to a shop, 1893; MS.1825.0798; 4 pages (3 blank); 15 centimeters. (Box 3, Folder 43)
      Place: Fès. Signed by Mosheh Eliyahu Elbaz and others.
    - Testimony in the city of Fès, 1914; MS.1825.0814; 4 pages (3 blank); 26 centimeters. (Box 3, Folder 44)
      Place: Fès. Relating to Rahel bat Maimon Edre'i who meets with men at night in specific places like the cemetery. Signed by Abba Attia and Iyush Saadon. In Judeo-Arabic.
    - Legal document relating to an apartment rental, 1933; MS.1825.0818; 4 pages; 25 centimeters. (Box 32, Folder 3)
      Place: Fès. Names mentioned include Maimon Danan, head of the community, and members of the Ben Shoshan family. Printed form, filled in by hand. In French.
    - Document of inheritance, 1872; MS.1825.0843; 4 pages (2 blank); 30 centimeters. (Box 32, Folder 3)
      Place: Fès. Involved are two sisters and their brother.
    - Legal document, 1858; MS.1825.0844; 2 pages; 22 centimeters. (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - Legal document, 1862; MS.1825.0845; 4 pages (3 blank); 18 centimeters. (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - Legal decision regarding a will, 1860; MS.1825.0849; 20 pages; 19 centimeters. Pages damaged with some loss of text. (Box 3, Folder 45)
      Place: Fès. Includes an affirmation of the decision in Sefrou in 1862.
    - Document with regard to an inheritance, 1916; MS.1825.0851; 6 pages; 23 centimeters. Pages bound together. (Box 3, Folder 46)
      Place: Fès. Signed by Abba Attia, Yosef ben Naim, and others.
    - Letter from Shaul Ben Shoshan to his father, 1884; MS.1825.0856; 2 pages; 27 centimeters. Page is damaged. (Box 4, Folder 1)
      Place: Fès. Letter is written in Judeo-Arabic.
    - Collection of documents, 1849, 1856; MS.1825.0863; 32 pages (16 blank); 23 centimeters. (Box 4, Folder 2)
      Place: Fès. Copies of legal documents and decisions from Fès, 1849, responsa from 1856, a legal decision from 1880 and document relating to paying the debts of Yosef Shemuel ha-kohen, 1886.
    - Copies of various documents, 1864; MS.1825.0867; 2 pages; 30 centimeters. (Box 32, Folder 3)
    - Legal document, 1916; MS.1825.0868; 1 leaf; 15 centimeters. (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Legal document, 1913; MS.1825.0875; 4 pages (3 blank); 16 centimeters. (Box 4, Folder 3)
      Place: Fès. Signed by Yaakov Assaraf and Eliyahu Waknin.
    - Legal document, 1898; MS.1825.0876; 4 pages (2 blank); 15 centimeters. (Box 4, Folder 3)
      Place: Fès. Signed by Shaul ben Almas'ali, Shimon Asulin, and Maimon Ben Shoshan.
    - Legal document, 1906; MS.1825.0882; 4 pages (3 blank); 15 centimeters. (Box 4, Folder 4)
      Place: Fès. Barukh ben Ittah, Avraham Ben Shoshan and others.
    - Document from a woman named Hanah Makhluf, releasing the person who owed her money from any further demands, 1832; MS.1825.0887; 4 pages (3 blank); 11 centimeters. (Box 4, Folder 4)
      Place: Fès. Signed by Refael ha-Kohen and another sage.
    - Document with regard to collateral of a piece of real estate for a loan, 1868; MS.1825.0889; 4 pages (2 blank); 23 centimeters. (Box 32, Folder 3)
      Place: Fès. Signed by Avraham ha-Levi and Mosheh Attia.
    - Document regarding real estate owned by a woman, 1832; MS.1825.0891; 4 pages (3 blank); 23 centimeters. (Box 4, Folder 4)
      Place: Fès. Signed by Shelomoh ha-Kohen Skali.
    - Document in Arabic of an agreement between Yitshak ben Harosh and a Moslem man named Mohammed ben Ali ben al-Quaid as-Slasy, 1838; MS.1825.0892; 4 pages (1 blank); 15 centimeters. (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Bill relating to finances by Yitshak Shalem ben Malka and Yaakov ben Kobo, 1870; MS.1825.0897; 4 pages (1 blank); 18 centimeters. Torn with some damage to text. (Box 4, Folder 5)
      Place: Fès. The men received funds from Yosef Maimaran. Signed by [Walad Tsultan?] and [Shelomoh ben Natsam?].
    - Document concerning the purchase of a portion of a house, 1880; MS.1825.0901; 2 pages; 29 centimeters. (Box 4, Folder 5)
      Place: Fès. Yaakov ben-Harosh, a man from Meknès who lived in Fès, purchased the property from Maimon Ben Shoshan. Signed by Eliyahu ha-Kohen Skali.
    - Document of a woman who sold her share of two houses, 1872; MS.1825.0903; 4 pages ( 2 blank); 18 centimeters. (Box 4, Folder 5)
      Place: Fès. Signed by Shelomoh ha-Kohen Skali and another sage.
    - Document of a gift of a woman renouncing a claim on a piece of property, 1890; MS.1825.0907.1-.2; 8 pages (4 blank); 23 centimeters. (Box 32, Folder 4)
      Place: Fès. The woman is Reyna bat Masud ben Amozeg.
    - Document concerning a house in Fès, 1894; MS.1825.0908; 4 pages; 14 centimeters. (Box 4, Folder 6)
      Place: Fès. Among the signatories is Yaakov Assayag.
    - Document relating to real estate, Circa 1880-circa 1900; MS.1825.0911; 4 pages (3 blank); 16 centimeters. (Box 4, Folder 6)
      Place: Fès. Signed by Maimon Ben Shoshan, Shelomoh Sasson and Shelomoh Haguel.
    - Document invalidating a ketubah of a woman from Fès, 1865; MS.1825.0912; 4 pages (2 blank); 23 centimeters. Some damage with loss of text. (Box 32, Folder 4)
      Place: Fès. Signed by Mosheh Attia and Shaul Sultan.
    - Document regarding money, 1902; MS.1825.0915; 4 pages (3 blank); 15 centimeters. (Box 4, Folder 6)
      Place: Fès. One of the signers is Abba Attia.
    - Series of documents relating to real estate, 1906; MS.1825.0916; 1 leaf; 23 centimeters. Repair tape covering some text. (Box 4, Folder 6)
      Place: Fès. One of the signatures is of Shimon Hayim Eziyni.
    - Series of documents relating to real estate, 1900-1904; MS.1825.0917; 1 leaf; 30 centimeters. (Box 4, Folder 7)
      Place: Fès. One of the signers is Shelomoh Aturgeman.
    - Document of a loan, 1908; MS.1825.0919; 4 pages (3 blank); 23 centimeters. (Box 4, Folder 7)
      Place: Fès. Text regarding rules of ritual slaughtering by Refael Berdugo, with additions written and signed by Maimon Berdugo (Rav ha-mevin).
    - Letter in Judeo-Arabic with regard to a shipment of scrolls, mezuzot, and phylacteries, 1908; MS.1825.0923; 2 pages; 27 centimeters. (Box 4, Folder 7)
      Place: Fès. The letter was sent to Shalom ben 'Amran in Meknès by Yosef ben Issou, who admits that some of the items were not included in the shipment. The writer does not seem to be entirely forthright.
    - Series of eight documents, some written in Judeo-Arabic, 1910; MS.1825.0929; 2 pages; 23 centimeters. (Box 4, Folder 8)
      Place: Fès or Meknès. The documents are signed by Yaakov Mesas and David Halawah.